const questions = [
    {
        question: "The answer is really big. ?",
        optionA: "THE ANSWER.",
        optionB: "Really big.",
        optionC: "An elephant.",
        optionD: "The data given is insufficient.",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "You're 3rd place right now in a race. What place are you in when you pass the person in 2nd place?",
        optionA: "1st",
        optionB: "2nd",
        optionC: "3rd",
        optionD: "None of the above.",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "How many 0.5cm slices of bread can you cut from a whole bread that's 25cm long? ?",
        optionA: "1",
        optionB: "25",
        optionC: "39",
        optionD: "None of the above",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "30 days has ______ ?",
        optionA: "January",
        optionB: "December",
        optionC: "June",
        optionD: "August",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "They fly at night, you'd better run. These winged things are not much fun.?",
        optionA: "Birds",
        optionB: "Eagles",
        optionC: "Witches",
        optionD: "Bats",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Divide 30 by half and add ten. ?",
        optionA: "40.5",
        optionB: "50",
        optionC: "70",
        optionD: "NONE",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "A little bite will make you itch, make you sneeze, make you twitch.?",
        optionA: "Hamburgers",
        optionB: "Ant",
        optionC: "Mosquito",
        optionD: "Nick",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "A farmer has 17 sheep, all of them but 8 die. How many sheep are still standing? ?",
        optionA: "8",
        optionB: "9",
        optionC: "25",
        optionD: "35",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "Which of these numbers is an odd number ?",
        optionA: "Ten",
        optionB: "Twelve",
        optionC: "Eight",
        optionD: "Eleven",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: `"You Can't see me" is a popular saying by`,
        optionA: "Eminem",
        optionB: "Bill Gates",
        optionC: "Chris Brown",
        optionD: "John Cena",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Where is the world tallest building located ?",
        optionA: "Africa",
        optionB: "California",
        optionC: "Dubai",
        optionD: "Italy",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "His fangs are sharp, he likes your taste.?",
        optionA: "Lion",
        optionB: "Mosquito",
        optionC: "Vampire",
        optionD: "Bat",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },


    {
        question: "How many permanent teeth does a dog have ?",
        optionA: "38",
        optionB: "42",
        optionC: "40",
        optionD: "36",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "They grow much faster than bamboo. Take care or they'll come after you.?",
        optionA: "Ants",
        optionB: "Palm",
        optionC: "Tree",
        optionD: "Plants",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Need a hand, well you just wait. We'll lend a hand, we each have eight.?",
        optionA: "Ants",
        optionB: "Spiders",
        optionC: "Octopuses",
        optionD: "Roaches",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "How many months have 28 days??",
        optionA: "2",
        optionB: "1",
        optionC: "All of them.",
        optionD: "Depends if there's a leap year or not.",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "There are 45 apples in your basket. You take three apples out of the basket. How many apples are left?",
        optionA: "3",
        optionB: "42",
        optionC: "45",
        optionD: "I do not eat apple!",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Los Angeles is also known as ?",
        optionA: "Angels City",
        optionB: "Shining city",
        optionC: "City of Angels",
        optionD: "Lost Angels",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "Beware the ground on which you stand. The floor is quicker than the sand.",
        optionA: "Ocean",
        optionB: "Ground",
        optionC: "Storm",
        optionD: "Quicksand",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "How many sides does an hexagon have ?",
        optionA: "Six",
        optionB: "Sevene",
        optionC: "Four",
        optionD: "Five",
        correctOption: "optionA"
    },

    {
        question: "How many planets are currently in the solar system ?",
        optionA: "Eleven",
        optionB: "Seven",
        optionC: "Nine",
        optionD: "Eight",
        correctOption: "optionD"
    },

    {
        question: "Which Planet is the hottest ?",
        optionA: "Jupitar",
        optionB: "Mercury",
        optionC: "Earth",
        optionD: "Venus",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "where is the smallest bone in human body located?",
        optionA: "Toes",
        optionB: "Ears",
        optionC: "Fingers",
        optionD: "Nose",
        correctOption: "optionB"
    },

    {
        question: "How many hearts does an Octopus have ?",
        optionA: "One",
        optionB: "Two",
        optionC: "Three",
        optionD: "Four",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    },

    {
        question: "How many teeth does an adult human have ?",
        optionA: "28",
        optionB: "30",
        optionC: "32",
        optionD: "36",
        correctOption: "optionC"
    }

]


let shuffledQuestions = [] //empty array to hold shuffled selected questions out of all available questions

function handleQuestions() { 
    //function to shuffle and push 10 questions to shuffledQuestions array
//app would be dealing with 10questions per session
    while (shuffledQuestions.length <= 9) {
        const random = questions[Math.floor(Math.random() * questions.length)]
        if (!shuffledQuestions.includes(random)) {
            shuffledQuestions.push(random)
        }
    }
}


let questionNumber = 1 //holds the current question number
let playerScore = 0  //holds the player score
let wrongAttempt = 0 //amount of wrong answers picked by player
let indexNumber = 0 //will be used in displaying next question

// function for displaying next question in the array to dom
//also handles displaying players and quiz information to dom
function NextQuestion(index) {
    handleQuestions()
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[index]
    document.getElementById("question-number").innerHTML = questionNumber
    document.getElementById("player-score").innerHTML = playerScore
    document.getElementById("display-question").innerHTML = currentQuestion.question;
    document.getElementById("option-one-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionA;
    document.getElementById("option-two-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionB;
    document.getElementById("option-three-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionC;
    document.getElementById("option-four-label").innerHTML = currentQuestion.optionD;

}


function checkForAnswer() {
    const currentQuestion = shuffledQuestions[indexNumber] //gets current Question 
    const currentQuestionAnswer = currentQuestion.correctOption //gets current Question's answer
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option"); //gets all elements in dom with name of 'option' (in this the radio inputs)
    let correctOption = null

    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            //get's correct's radio input with correct answer
            correctOption = option.labels[0].id
        }
    })

    //checking to make sure a radio input has been checked or an option being chosen
    if (options[0].checked === false && options[1].checked === false && options[2].checked === false && options[3].checked == false) {
        document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "flex"
    }

    //checking if checked radio button is same as answer
    options.forEach((option) => {
        if (option.checked === true && option.value === currentQuestionAnswer) {
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "green"
            playerScore++ //adding to player's score
            indexNumber++ //adding 1 to index so has to display next question..
            //set to delay question number till when next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++
            }, 1000)
        }

        else if (option.checked && option.value !== currentQuestionAnswer) {
            const wrongLabelId = option.labels[0].id
            document.getElementById(wrongLabelId).style.backgroundColor = "red"
            document.getElementById(correctOption).style.backgroundColor = "green"
            wrongAttempt++ //adds 1 to wrong attempts 
            indexNumber++
            //set to delay question number till when next question loads
            setTimeout(() => {
                questionNumber++
            }, 1000)
        }
    })
}



//called when the next button is called
function handleNextQuestion() {
    checkForAnswer() //check if player picked right or wrong option
    unCheckRadioButtons()
    //delays next question displaying for a second just for some effects so questions don't rush in on player
    setTimeout(() => {
        if (indexNumber <= 9) {
//displays next question as long as index number isn't greater than 9, remember index number starts from 0, so index 9 is question 10
            NextQuestion(indexNumber)
        }
        else {
            handleEndGame()//ends game if index number greater than 9 meaning we're already at the 10th question
        }
        resetOptionBackground()
    }, 1000);
}

//sets options background back to null after display the right/wrong colors
function resetOptionBackground() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    options.forEach((option) => {
        document.getElementById(option.labels[0].id).style.backgroundColor = ""
    })
}

// unchecking all radio buttons for next question(can be done with map or foreach loop also)
function unCheckRadioButtons() {
    const options = document.getElementsByName("option");
    for (let i = 0; i < options.length; i++) {
        options[i].checked = false;
    }
}

// function for when all questions being answered
function handleEndGame() {
    let remark = null
    let remarkColor = null

    // condition check for player remark and remark color
    if (playerScore <= 3) {
        remark = "Bad Grades, Keep Practicing."
        remarkColor = "red"
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 4 && playerScore < 7) {
        remark = "Average Grades, You can do better."
        remarkColor = "orange"
    }
    else if (playerScore >= 7) {
        remark = "Excellent, Keep the good work going."
        remarkColor = "green"
    }
    const playerGrade = (playerScore / 10) * 100

    //data to display to score board
    document.getElementById('remarks').innerHTML = remark
    document.getElementById('remarks').style.color = remarkColor
    document.getElementById('grade-percentage').innerHTML = playerGrade
    document.getElementById('wrong-answers').innerHTML = wrongAttempt
    document.getElementById('right-answers').innerHTML = playerScore
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "flex"

}

//closes score modal, resets game and reshuffles questions
function closeScoreModal() {
    questionNumber = 1
    playerScore = 0
    wrongAttempt = 0
    indexNumber = 0
    shuffledQuestions = []
    NextQuestion(indexNumber)
    document.getElementById('score-modal').style.display = "none"
}

//function to close warning modal
function closeOptionModal() {
    document.getElementById('option-modal').style.display = "none"
}